Guide to the Richard Wright Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
- Personal Papers, 1927-1978; Series III; 3.5; (8 boxes)
  - Questionnaire - "Poll of Experts: Questions on Negro-White Relations" from Bureau of Applied Social Research [blank], 1945 (Box 118, Folder 1893)
  - Questionnaire on writing [blank], n.d. (Box 118, Folder 1894)
  - Radio broadcast script, "Die Negerroman in den USA", 1964 (Box 118, Folder 1895)
  - Real estate documents, 1940-48 (Box 118, Folder 1896)
  - Receipts
    - General, 1940-47 (Box 118, Folder 1897)
    - Hospital, 1947-49 (Box 118, Folder 1898)
    - Hotels, 1949-55 (Box 118, Folder 1899-1900)
    - Travel, 1940-57 (Box 118, Folder 1901-1902)
    - Work done by Richard Wright, 1945-56 (Box 118, Folder 1903)
  - Removal order for storage, 1941 (Box 118, Folder 1904)
    - Spectrum in Black: Poems by 20th Century Black Poets - 33 1/3 RPM double LP set, 1971 (Box 142 (Record album storage), Folder #1904a)
    - Native Son, by Richard Wright, read by James Earl Jones - 33 1/3 RPM double LP set, 1973 (Box 142 (Record album storage), Folder #1904b)
    - Black Boy, read by Brock Peters - 33 1/3 RPM double LP set, 1970 (Box 142 (Record album storage), Folder #1904c)
  - Report card for Richard Wright from Englewood Accredited Evening High School, 1933 (Box 118, Folder 1905)
  - Resume for Edward K. Moss, n.d. (Box 118, Folder 1906)
  - Schedule and announcement of Richard Wright's appearance at Fisk University, 1943 Apr (Box 118, Folder 1907)
  - Selective Service registration cards, 1941-45 (Box 118, Folder 1908)
  - Sketch of Richard Wright (in ink), n.d. (Box 118, Folder 1909)
  - Sketch of Richard Wright [by Skogholm?] (in pencil), 1949 (Box 118, Folder 1910)
  - Sketches of African-Americans by Eduardo Vicente (two, in ink), n.d. (Box 118, Folder 1911)
  - Social Security card for Richard Wright, 1937 Jun 14 (Box 118, Folder 1912)
  - Socialist Labor Party Platform, 1944 (Box 118, Folder 1913)
  - Song lyrics sheets (spirituals and jazz) (Box 118, Folder 1914)
  - Spingarn medal
    See: Oversize, Box 130, folder 1976
  - Tax declaration, France, 1948 Feb 5 (Box 118, Folder 1915)
  - Théatre Populaire Africaine stationery [one blank sheet], n.d. (Box 118, Folder 1916)
  - Tract - "The Flame" by Andra, 1940 Oct (Box 118, Folder 1917)
  - Travel documents for trip to Ghana, 1953 (Box 118, Folder 1918)
  - War ration books, 1943, n.d. (Box 118, Folder 1919)
  - White Mountain Writers' Conference Bulletin [fragment], 1941 (Box 118, Folder 1920)
  - Youth in Focus photo contest brochure, 1940 (Box 118, Folder 1921)
- Subject Files, 1929-1959; Series IV; 3.25; (8 boxes)
  Series IV, Subject Files, is arranged alphabetically.
  - American Council on Race Relations, 1945 (Box 132, Folder 1979)
  - Conference of Negro Writers and Artists, 1959 (Box 132, Folder 1980-1981)
  - Conference on Race Relations, 1944 Mar (Box 132, Folder 1982)
  - Ghana, 1945-59, n.d. (Box 132, Folder 1983-1985)
  - Ghana, 1945-59, n.d. (Box 133, Folder 1986-1992)
  - Ghana, 1945-59, n.d. (Box 134, Folder 1993-1997)
  - Ghana, 1945-59, n.d. (Box 135, Folder 1998-1999)
  - Indonesia, ca. 1950-59 (Box 135, Folder 2000-2006)
  - Indonesia, ca. 1950-59 (Box 136, Folder 2007)
  - Karpman, Ben, 1931-42 (Box 136, Folder 2008-2009)
  - Literature, n.d. (Box 136, Folder 2010)
  - Miscellaneous, 1938-59 (Box 136, Folder 2011-2012)
  - Miscellaneous, 1938-59 (Box 137, Folder 2013)
  - Politics, 1942-49 (Box 137, Folder 2014-2016)
  - Racial issues
    - Clippings - general, ca. 1941-57 (Box 137, Folder 2017)
    - "Negros in War" and labor issues, 1940-41 (Box 137, Folder 2018)
    - Printed material, 1929-59 (Box 137, Folder 2019-2020)
    - Printed material, 1929-59 (Box 138, Folder 2021-2022)
    - Typescripts and carbons of articles, papers, and reports, ca. 1940-55 (Box 139, Folder 2023-2024)
  - Spain, 1939-55 (Box 139, Folder 2025-2027)
    See also: Oversize, Box 122, folder 1968b
  - Wertham, Frederic, 1942-52 (Box 139, Folder 2028)
  - Wiltwyck School for Boys (including City-wide Citizens' Committee on Harlem), 1942-45 (Box 139, Folder 2029)
  - Writers' Organizations, 1941, n.d. (Box 139, Folder 2030)
- Oversize, 20.2; (15 boxes)
  Series IV, Oversize, consists of items from Series I, II, and III. Each item indicates the box and folder number where it is housed, since certain items are not arranged in strict hierarchical order.
  - Writings
    - ANTHOLOGIES (Containing works by Wright)
      - American Stuff, 1937 (Box 119, Folder 1922)
      - The God That Failed, 1949-52 (Box 119, Folder 1922)
    - ARTICLES, ESSAYS AND REPORTS
      - "L'homme du Sud," printed version, France Etats-Unis, 1950 Dec (Box 119, Folder 1923)
      - "How Jim Crow Feels", printed version (as "Dans le monde entier je sais reconnaître un négre du Sud"), Paris-Matin, 1946 Jun-Jul (Box 119, Folder 1923)
      - Scrapbook of articles published in Daily Worker, 1937 Jun-Dec (Box 123, Folder 1969)
      - Blurb for Oswald, Marianne, One Small Voice, poster advertisement for French translation, quoting Wright, [1945?] (Box 119, Folder 1924)
    - BOOKS
      - Black Boy
        - Plate proofs (including revised title pages changed to Black Boy dated Sep 21 1944), 1944 Apr-May (Box 124, Folder 1970)
        - Clippings - Advertisements, 1945 (Box 119, Folder 1925)
        - Clippings - Reviews, 1944-70 (Box 119, Folder 1925)
        - Clippings - Best Seller lists, 1945-46 (Box 119, Folder 1925)
        - "Black Boy: A Negro writes a bitter autobiography," photoessay in Life by George Karger [with Italian translation of article for Il Politecnico, 1945 Jun 4 (Box 119, Folder 1926)
        - French translation (Jeunesse Noire) - announcements and reviews - clippings, 1947-65 (Box 119, Folder 1927)
        - Book jacket for Italian translation, Ragazzo Negro, n.d. (Box 119, Folder 1927)
      - Black Hope
        - Background research material - clippings and printed material, 1937-43 (Box 119, Folder 1928)
      - Black Power
        - Clippings - Reviews, 1945-57 (Box 119, Folder 1929)
        - German translation [ Schwarze Macht ]- Reviews - clippings, 1956-66 (Box 119, Folder 1929)
        - Reviews of French, Italian and Swedish translations - clippings, 1955, 1957 (Box 119, Folder 1929)
        - Contact sheets [49 prints] (Box 141, Folder 2038-46)
          Formerly housed in Box 24, folders 369-70
      - The Color Curtain
        - Book jacket, 1956 (Box 119, Folder 1930)
        - Announcements and reviews - clippings, 1955-58, n.d. (Box 119, Folder 1930)
        - Reviews of Dutch, French and German translations - clippings, 1956-58, n.d. (Box 119, Folder 1930a)
      - The Long Dream
        - Reviews - clippings, 1958-59 (Box 119, Folder 1931)
      - Native Son
        - Background materials - clippings, 1938-39 (Box 120, Folder 1932-1935)
        - Clippings on racism and crime found with background materials, 1941-47 (Box 120, Folder 1936)
        - Illustrations by Clarence G. Hackett [ten block prints], 1942 (Box 120a, Folder 1936a-j)
        - Book jackets, 1940-[43?] (Box 120, Folder 1937)
        - Clippings - Advertisements, 1940-42 (Box 120, Folder 1938)
        - Clippings - Reviews, 1940-72 (Box 120, Folder 1939)
        - Clippings - Reviews in German, Spanish, Swedish and Yiddish, 1940 (Box 120, Folder 1940)
        - Clippings - Letters to the Editor, 1940 (Box 120, Folder 1941)
        - Excerpt published in PM Magazine, "If Bigger Wasn't Black and If He Had Money And If They'd Let Him Go to Aviation School, He Could Fly", 1941 May 7 (Box 120, Folder 1942)
        - Serialization in The People's Voice, 1942 (Box 120, Folder 1942)
        - French translation, Un Enfant du Pays, Announcements and reviews - clippings, 1947-48 (Box 120, Folder 1942)
      - The Outsider
        - Clippings - advertisements and reviews, 1953 (Box 121, Folder 1943)
        - Swedish translation, Utanför - book jacket, n.d. (Box 121, Folder 1944)
        - Norwegian translation, Vidnet - clipping - review, 1954 Sep (Box 121, Folder 1944)
      - Pagan Spain
        - Clippings - reviews, 1957, 1960 (Box 121, Folder 1945)
        - German translation, Heidnisches Spanien - clippings - advertisements and reviews, 1958-60 (Box 121, Folder 1945)
      - 12 Million Black Voices
        - Book jacket, 1941 (Box 121, Folder 1946)
        - Clippings - announcements, reviews and advertisements, 1941-63 (Box 121, Folder 1946)
      - Uncle Tom's Children
        - Clippings - announcements, reviews and advertisements, 1938-65 (Box 121, Folder 1947)
      - White Man, Listen!
        - "Psychological Reactions of Oppressed People" [Chapter 1] - lecture in Norway, poster, 1956 (Box 121, Folder 1948)
        - Book jacket, [1957] (Box 121, Folder 1949)
        - Clippings - reviews and advertisements, 1957-59 (Box 121, Folder 1949)
    - FILM SCENARIOS
      - "Native Son" [adapted with Pierre Chenal]
        - Exhibitor's Campaign Book with Bulletin, [1951] (Box 121, Folder 1950)
        - Poster, [1951] (Box bsd, folder 2031)
        - Poster, [1951] (Box bsd, folder 2032)
        - Clippings - announcements, reviews and features [in English, French and Italian], 1947-51 (Box 121, Folder 1951)
    - HAIKU
      - Collection of 824 verses, typescript (verses cut out and mounted on 20 large cardboard sheets) (Box bsd, folder 2033–bsd, folder 2035)
    - PLAYS
      - "Native Son"
        - Leaflets, 1941 (Box 121, Folder 1952)
        - Clippings - announcements, reviews, notices and features, 1940-78 (Box 121, Folder 1953)
        - Clipping - article from Spanish publication, Norte, 1941 Aug (Box 121, Folder 1953)
        - Programs and clippings for productions in Argentina, Czechoslovakia, England, France, and Sweden, 1945-48 (Box 121, Folder 1954)
          Includes signed photograph of Narciso Ibañez Menta, star of Argentinian production
    - REVIEWS
      - "'Sixty Million Jobs' as three writers see it," review of 60,000,000 Jobs by Henry Wallace, printed version, n.d. (Box 122, Folder 1955)
    - STORIES
      - "Early Days in Chicago," printed version (as "Débuts à Chicago), Les Temps Modernes (with clipping - review), 1946-47 (Box 122, Folder 1956)
      - "Fire and Cloud," printed version, The Daily Worker, including profile of Wright: "An Author Discusses His Craft", 1938 Dec (Box 125, Folder 1971)
      - "The Man Who Killed A Shadow," printed version (as "L'homme qui tua une ombre"), Les Lettres Françaises, 1946 Oct 4 (Box 122, Folder 1956)
    - TRANSLATIONS
      - Diop, Alioune, [Statement of aims for Presence Africaine ] translated and adapted [in collaboration with Thomas Diop] as "Niam N'Goura or Presence Africaine's Raison D'être"
        - Announcement of article and subsequent association of Wright with Présence Africaine - clippings, 1948-49 (Box 122, Folder 1957)
    - WRITINGS OF OTHERS
      - Owen, Charles, "Negroes and the War" [article] (Box 122, Folder 1958)
  - Correspondence
    - Brown, Basil Breven, 1940-45 (Box 122, Folder 1959)
  - Personal Papers
    - Audiotapes [30 reel-to-reel], 1960, 1964, n.d. (Box 126, Folder 1972)
    - Audiotapes - Interview tapes (Entretiens avec R. Wright), 1956-61 (Box 126a, Folder 1972a)
      - Tape A: "Un rapport mal etabli", 1960 October; 1 (Box 126a)
      - Tape B: "Le roman américain", undated (Box 126a)
      - Tape C: "Fishbelly", 1960 October; 1 (Box 126a)
      - Tape D: "Entre deux mondes", 1960 October; 1 (Box 126a)
      - Tape E: "Entretien", 1960 November; 1 (Box 126a)
      - Tape F: "Un noir américain en France", 1960 October; 1 (Box 126a)
      - Tape G: "Un roman noir chez les Blanco", 1960 November; 1 (Box 126a)
      - "Hommage a Richard Wright", undated; 1 (Box 126a)
      - Unidentified, undated; 1 (Box 126a)
    - Camera [Contax 35mm in brown leather case - without lens], n.d. (Box 127, Folder 1973)
    - Clippings
      - Appearance by Richard Wright in North Carolina, 1940 (Box 122, Folder 1960)
      - Interviews and Profiles - in Dutch, Norwegian and Swedish, 1946-60 (Box 122, Folder 1961)
      - Interviews and Profiles - in English, 1940-56 (Box 122, Folder 1962)
      - Interviews and Profiles - in French, 1946-60 (Box 122, Folder 1963)
      - Interviews and Profiles - in German, 1946-60 (Box 122, Folder 1963)
      - Interviews and Profiles - in Italian, 1948-57 (Box 122, Folder 1964)
      - Literary Map of U.S.A. with reference to Native Son, 1941 Dec 3 (Box 122, Folder 1965)
      - Projects involving Richard Wright, 1934-56 (Box 122, Folder 1965)
      - Various subjects - including racial issues, black celebrities and friends of Richard Wright, 1927-60 (Box 122, Folder 1966)
    - Drawings by Julia Wright, 1945 (Box 122, Folder 1967)
    - Eyeglasses [4 pair with cases], n.d. (Box 128, Folder 1974)
    - Eyeglasses [9 pair loose and one pair lenses] (Box 129, Folder 1975)
    - Interview with Richard Wright by Betty Wells, broadcast by KRNT, Des Moines, Iowa (16" audiodisc), 1945 Nov 15 (Box 129a, Folder 1975a)
    - Invitations and announcements
      - Appearances by Richard Wright, 1936-56 (Box 122, Folder 1968)
    - Mock Newspaper, The Chicago View, with headline: "Dick Wright Noted Author Off to N.Y.", n.d. (Box 122, Folder 1968)
    - Posters with poems: "The Exodus" and "Take Dad's Advice and Don't be a Fool!" by A. Namderloc (Box 122, Folder 1968a)
    - Spingarn medal, 1941 (Box 130, Folder 1976)
    - Film - Screen test for Native Son: Richard Wright at Bigger Thomas in 3 scenes, 2 takes each, running time approximately 7-1/2 minutes. Silent and track print., 1948; 2 (Box 140, Folder 2036)
  - Subject Files
    - Spain, 1954 Dec (Box 122, Folder 1968b)
- Restricted Fragile Oversize, 1.25; (1 box)
  Restricted Fragile Oversize contains oversize fragile originals. The containers of items removed for cold storage have been retained. The material may only be seen with the permission of the appropriate curator. A digital surrogate of material is available for reference.
  - Box 140, folder 2036 (Box cs, folder 2037)